This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
>> [music]
>> Are you a tech-savvy developer with an
inquisitive mind?
SE Radio has an opening for a new
volunteer host to join the team and
produce five episodes per year.
To apply, please follow the instructions
on our website at se-radio.net/contact.
>> For Software Engineering Radio, this is
Robert Blumen.
I have with me today Sahil Walia. Sahil
is a senior technical architect at
Snowflake and he has published many
papers on data engineering and
artificial intelligence. Today, Sahil
and I will be talking about Apache
Iceberg. Sahil, welcome to Software
Engineering Radio.
>> Thanks for having me, Robert. Excited to
be here.
>> So, anything else you'd like to say to
listeners about your background before
we get into the topic?
>> Absolutely. Thank you first of all for
the opportunity, Robert. I am Sahil
Walia. I'm a senior technical architect
working with Snowflake. I specialize in
data engineering workloads and
specifically open lakehouse
architectures. I try to migrate
customers outside of their old
architectures into the contemporary new
architectures like lakehouses, Iceberg,
and make sure it's interoperable for
other environments.
>> Sahil, you just threw out a bunch of
buzzwords that sound very relevant to
the topic today, Apache Iceberg. I will
be getting into defining what all of
those mean. Let's start out with a
background question. You can run these
OLAP workloads less efficiently on a
general-purpose database. What is the
cutover point where you want to switch
to a specialized OLAP
for your workload.
>> Absolutely. For the audience who's not
familiar, OLTP is essentially
transactional, OLAP is essentially
analytical. And there's no certain
benchmark I would put, but there are
certain criteria as I would look for.
So, one of the examples I would look for
is when you're looking for latency
budget of milliseconds, you want to stay
in OLTP world. But when your latency
budget is in about seconds and minutes
and your audience is mostly analytical,
training the ML workloads on data and
it's not dependent on transactional
data, I would move towards the OLAP.
Another thing that I look for is where
you have read heavy aggregations and you
have wide tables. Those are essentially
a few of the good candidates where an
OLAP would make more sense. But if you
need primary key enforcements and for
example, you want to do frequent single
row rights, in that scenario I would
maintain the OLTP.
>> We're talking about workloads with
latency budget of many seconds to
minutes. What are the size of data sets
that require that amount of time?
>> Sure. If I understand your question
right, Robert, you're asking at what
latency we should be thinking about
moving towards the OLAP. Is that right?
>> No, I'm saying if you have a workload
that you're willing to wait for several
minutes, you must be dealing with a very
large amount of data. How big is that
data set?
>> Oh, that can start from anywhere about
gigabytes to terabytes and petabytes.
Iceberg, which the topic we are going to
talk about, essentially can handle
petabytes of data. And Netflix, who are
the where the creators created Iceberg,
they actually benchmarked on petabytes
of data. Think of petabytes as about, I
would say, 220 million songs. So, that's
a big data set.
>> What are some other domains where you
have data sets of that size?
>> Banking is one of them, healthcare is
one of them, and then clickstream data,
essentially meaning how you're clicking
on the app or interface, and then
healthcare is another one of them.
>> Let's now talk about some of the terms
that will enable us to have a
conversation about iceberg. Data lake
and in recent years I'm hearing about
data lake houses. Explain what those
are.
>> Sure. The way I would think from data
lake and data lake houses to take a step
back first to a data warehouse. So,
essentially data warehouse is anything
which manages your analytical workloads.
They were essentially meant to be very
structured schema on right kind of thing
and optimized for BI. And then later
came a world of data lake with a cloud
world wherein you had S3, ADLS, what you
could do with this you could manage your
raw files into a cloud bucket, dumped
into a cheap storage. But, the challenge
that the teams were dealing with was it
was essentially creating a data dump,
right? And data swamp, and they were not
able to manage it, there was no
structure that the teams were used to,
and the schema on right behaviors the
team were used to in the data warehouse
world. So, then essentially the
challenge came and we're like, how can
we get benefits of the both world? And
that's where data lakehouse come in. So,
the analogy I usually use is that a data
warehouse is like a filing cabinet,
while a data lake is kind of a U-Haul
storage, and you can put that U-Haul
storage, and within that U-Haul storage
I can you can put a data warehouse,
which is a filing cabinet, and you can
manage it properly. So, you have the
lakehouse storage, which is cheaper, but
you have warehouse-like a structure and
warehouse-like transactions. So, data
should be easily accessible. You have
guarantees associated to it. Let's say
business is running on it, and it
provides you a lot more clarity. Happy
to double-click here, Robert.
>> Yeah, I want to go to that a little bit.
So, what I understood is the data
warehouse you're talking about a schema
that has invariants where it's much
easier to extract data from it because
you know how the data is aligned or the
data types are. You go to the other
extreme what you're calling a swamp,
which doesn't sound like a great living
space where data might not have been
regularized, cleaned, normalized,
therefore much harder to query. Is that
roughly what you said?
>> That's correct. Absolutely right. And
data warehouses were essentially
curated, right? So, there had to be a
use case, and you'll create a data
warehouse. But data lakes weren't
curated for a reason. And what was
essentially happening is it was a
append-only. You were putting files. The
great thing was you could put any sort
of files and those kind of things, and
you will manage them at the read time.
But when you're managing at the read
time, it created a lot more of burden.
So, let's go back with the same analogy.
Say you have put your winter coat in
that giant storage locker, but now you
need to find it. And in order for it to
serve you, it just takes so much time.
>> So, the point I want to explore here
about these data formats versus the
processing. If I think about Postgres,
it can be in most people it is a black
box. There's an engine, and it sits on
top of some kind of file format. I don't
have to know what that file format is in
order to use Postgres. Now, there are
tools like change data capture and some
replication products that understand
Postgres log formats and can read them.
But for the most part, these are very
tightly coupled things. Now, I wouldn't
then say, "Well, I'm going to get my
Postgres file formats and run Oracle on
top of it." It just they're very One is
engineered for the other. I have a quote
here from Confluent's website, which I
will read. It says, "In recent years,
we've witnessed the rise of headless
data infrastructure. Companies are
building a more open lakehouse in cloud
object storage that's accessible by any
number of tools." Is this tight coupling
from the database world between the
format and the engine? Is that breaking
down to where you mix and match?
>> Yeah, so I think you are bringing the
right point with the right background.
In the world of data, a lot of the
things were good, but they were tightly
coupled. So, you have your storage
engine, and then you have your compute
engine, and any other engine vector as
enhancements are built on top of it.
But, as a data team, you wouldn't have
access to it. So, you couldn't make
decisions, or you couldn't change the
level of compute or change the level of
storage what you wanted, right? So, the
Confluent blog you're talking about is
yes, this is about the headless data
infrastructure, which essentially means
in my mind as your data lives separate
to your compute. And now, you can scale
your storage and compute separately. It
doesn't stop only there. The advantage
is now team get is say, you have data in
S3, right? It can be accessed by
multiple engines now. You don't have to
maintain multiple copies, right? And
that's the way it's kind of headless.
And then, you can bring your own
compute, say Spark, or let's say you
want to do Databricks, or you want to do
let's say Snowflake, you can connect any
of them to that data and start running
your say analytics workload on top of
it.
>> Okay, I think we're ready now to talk
about what is Apache Iceberg. Where does
it fit into this landscape we've been
sketching out?
>> Yeah, we did talk about data lake houses
and Apache Iceberg enable that. And we
did talk about the headless
infrastructure, right? Apache Iceberg
enable that. So, let's dissect it a
little bit, right? But to provide a
little bit of background, it started
with Netflix. In Netflix, they were
dealing with petabyte scales of data.
They were having a lot of issues with
their hive systems at the time, right?
So, they wanted something which can help
them manage their metadata better. And
in short term, I would put Iceberg as a
open table format. It doesn't stop
there. It defines how you organize your
data files, but also the metadata files.
So, multiple engines can safely read and
write the same table, as I was alluding
to, right? And it has few key
components. So, one is called Iceberg
spec or specification. And the way I
would think of it is like by the
committers or by the committee, they put
a rule document, right? And that rule
document is something engines follow. It
tells you the standard or it tells you
how you need to follow the specification
for it to be interoperable, right? And
then there are libraries. Essentially,
libraries are essentially Java, Python,
Go. To boil it down, it essentially
means that it's a Iceberg implementation
for Java, Iceberg implementation for
Python, or let's say Iceberg
implementation for us. And the last
thing is the REST catalog. It allows the
standardized HTTP API catalog
operations. So, it lets other engines
connect via HTTP commands, to put it
simply.
>> This is something like
XML where it was an open data format and
any provider could implement bindings in
any language they want.
>> Yes, they can implement, but right now
the bindings that you talked about are
limited to as I remember Java, Python,
Rust and Go. So, those are the four ones
right now. I think there's a C++ one as
well. But, these implementations what I
have seen in my experiences are not
something a lot of team invest time on
but what they invest time on is how
those are integrated with the catalogs
because catalogs is something which
enables that accessibility of the data
or writing to that data.
>> I think I should ask you then to explain
what is the catalog, what's in it?
>> Sure, a catalog does a lot of things.
But, in the world of Iceberg it
essentially says when a engine goes to a
catalog it tells you okay catalog, I
need this table. It contains the rich
metadata of that particular table. So,
then engines can go through that JSON
files in technical world and inspect and
understand how it should prune the
queries if it is reading it and how it
should write the files if it is writing
it. And then they do other work as well.
For example, governance and those kind
of things. I don't want to go into that.
But, catalog is basically a point access
to that particular table.
>> Is this similar to what might be called
schema introspection in some data
products?
>> I may not be able to answer that
honestly. Do you want to double click on
that? Do you want to give an example?
>> Yeah, in most SQL systems you can say
describe table or show schema for table
and it will show you
>> Yes.
>> columns, constraints
>> Yeah, so that's how it does it. Thanks
for the clarification. So, when you're
basically going to that particular
describe statement what essentially
engine is doing is inspecting that JSON
file and that JSON file has a lot more
details. Happy to jump into details like
what those can have and how it's the
whole architecture.
>> We might come back to that. I want to do
some more high-level. You've talked
about the format that the files can live
pretty much anywhere on S3 or any type
of blob storage or on a regular file
system. For situating Apache Iceberg in
the landscape, is there anything you
would compare it to or is it the first
of its kind?
>> Nothing comes to my mind in relation to
the data as such data field, but I would
put it in the world of USBC. So, USBC is
something you can plug into your
MacBook, you can plug into your laptop,
you can charge your phone with it. So,
it's kind of a common connector and
that's the way I would think about it.
>> What is the history? Was this a
consortium of companies that all had the
same problem or was it invented by an
open-source engineer?
>> Sure. So, it started with Netflix, but
there has been active contribution in
its early years by Apple and by other
data companies. And these contributions,
essentially when it was becoming
successful, led it to be donating to
Apache Software Foundation. It got
incubated and then it got accepted and
it has been part of the Apache Software
Foundation.
>> We're talking about these agnostic
layers. You can store it wherever you
want on any cloud, any file system,
anything can read it. One of the reasons
that the storage format and the engine
were so tightly coupled is that the
storage was designed in a particular way
to reflect the physical nature of how
data was getting moved off of some kind
of persistent format and into memory
taking into account the IO rates, the
number of spindles, the adjacency of
things on disks such that the
performance of the engine would be
reasonable, especially for large data
sets. Do we give up something in
performance if we stick it on S3, which
no one outside of Amazon even knows how
it works?
>> That's a very valid question. And in
early years, when the Iceberg So,
currently Iceberg is on V3 spec, just
like any versions of iPhone, similarly
on the V3 spec. In the early years of
Iceberg, there was a lot of
discrepancies in terms of benchmarks,
right? And a lot of engines that were
closed, they knew their files, and they
could optimize for it better. But in the
last, I would say 3 to 4 years, there
has been convergence towards the
Iceberg, and even the vendors now are
pushing really hard, going towards the
Iceberg, and making their engines more
compatible, or I would say faster
towards that. And the recent benchmarks,
to answer your question, have been
showing these days that it's effectively
same, or sometimes better, in the
performance. In terms of S3, you're
absolutely right. You are leaving the
world of vendors in term of lock-in, but
you're still locked in turn kind of with
AWS. And AWS has your S3, and that's
where you manage your storage. But the
good part with S3 is you can do First of
all, it's very cheap, about $23 per
terabyte. So, it gives them cheaper
rates compared to vendors, right? And
then companies manage their own data.
So, tomorrow, let's say you are working
with vendor X, but with the innovation,
vendor X has been very behind, right?
Tomorrow, a brand new company comes with
a shiny object, you want to move to that
vendor Y. You still hold your data. You
still manage your data. You just need to
change the engine. So, now you don't
have to do those messy migrations,
wherein you basically have a lot of
table stakes highly product, which goes
down, and you do a proper planning
rather it should be ideally a plug and
play depending on how data moves world
moves.
>> The point I'm trying to get at is the
extent that you have all this
interoperability and abstraction layers
you make fewer guarantees about how
things work versus Postgres or Oracle
that owns the entire stack all the way
down to the file system they can make
very strong assumptions. So when you
talk about vendors and benchmarks do you
mean the vendors of the engines have all
tuned their engines or do you mean the
storage vendors like Amazon has said hey
Iceberg runs really well on S3. We've
done some magic stuff inside S3 that's
going to make it very friendly to your
Iceberg formats.
>> Okay, thanks for clarifying question.
Yeah, I meant that data vendors like for
example Oracle, Snowflake, Databricks as
an example not particularly S3 and these
I'm just not limiting the storage to S3.
You can do ADLS if you want Azure you
can do Google Cloud as well, right? And
can you repeat your question did I
answer your question or
>> My question is large workloads move
petabytes of data often you're
constrained by the IO rate of the
physical device or devices where your
data is. You can only move data off of
the device at whatever rate it supports
and is there a uniformity
of IO capacity across all different
substrates or people just say well,
yeah, I mean S3 is slow or blob storage
is slow but I can live with that because
it's cheap and it's a trade-off we make.
>> Sure. Yeah, let's talk about it. So over
here S3 has its own limitations. So
let's say if you're calling the S3 API,
you can only do so much of list
operations. So say you have records
which are billions in numbers, right? On
the original table but you only need
thousand of them. So, the beauty of
Iceberg is it has very rich metadata.
So, in the world of, let's say, Hive or
anything, what you would do is you'll go
to that particular directory and list
all the files in that directory. But,
the metadata is so rich in Iceberg that
it is at the file level. So, what really
happens is instead of making those
thousands API calls or hundred API
calls, Iceberg is really making only 10
or 15 API calls, and that essentially
helps you fetch data faster. And then,
that helps you with your S3 throttling
and everything.
>> Okay. What I think you might be saying
is maybe on Postgres or coffee out of
poorly designed query and it's doing a
table scan. It's a 50 GB table and it
ends up needing to read 50 GB that the
design of Iceberg, it's so smart that it
can have you reading 1 GB that has the
GB you need, and so that's inherently
faster than reading 50 GB regardless of
how you fast your IO is on that
substrate. Something like that.
>> Exactly. Yeah, so there are two
components to, right? One is the
metadata being rich, and another is your
engine as well as the warehouse and the
computer using on that, right? So, let's
say if you have a larger compute, you
will have more RAM and those kind of
things, but you're also limited with the
metadata as well. So, it's a combination
of both. I will marry them together. I
wouldn't separate them together in terms
of optimizing it, right? And finding the
data faster. But, your point on the
Iceberg, I plan to cover that if we have
time, the Iceberg architecture, how the
metadata is laid out. But, the metadata
is so rich and it at the file level that
it lets you prune or basically skip the
files which are not relevant at the back
end.
>> A new A new
for software excellence is here.
The IEEE Computer Society created the
software certifications to help you
evaluate candidates and encourage growth
across your teams.
Find out how to turn your individual
contributors into a unified team that
delivers excellence at
computer.org/certification.
>> Well, let's just let's talk about some
of the queries and the metadata. When
you're using Iceberg, what does the
interface look like to programmer? Are
you doing select or something that looks
familiar?
>> Yeah, the data engineers or the
engineers who are working with Iceberg,
they don't have to understand what
Iceberg implementation look like. They
just need to worry about the SQL or the
Python they know. So, as an example, if
you know select queries, insert queries,
update queries, other things are managed
by the engines, right? Because they're
integrating with the rest catalog. Now,
let's talk about it. So, let's say if
you're running a select query in SQL,
it's pretty much the same select query
you will run in Iceberg. If you're
running the insert query, you'll run the
same insert query in it's kind of a ANSI
standard SQL that you run. So, you don't
have to learn that. What you need to
learn is about the architecture
patterns, right? How the Iceberg handles
data, how Iceberg handles metadata, how
read operations happens, how write
operation happens, what metadata files
are. Because if you don't know those
things, you may not be able to optimize
for your workloads.
>> I'm reading about Iceberg, there's
discussion of time travel queries. Can
you explain what that is?
>> Absolutely. So, time travel is basically
I want to go in the past at a certain
time. And you can do it so many ways,
right? You can say, I want to go back
and see how the data look like 5 days
ago. And assume you have a lot more
events and you're doing something, let's
say you're doing a machine learning
model or you're doing some DML and your
code has changed now and your data looks
a little different. Oh, you will like,
"Oh my god, I messed it up. I want to
back up. I want to go back to the old
state and see how it looks." So, you
what you can basically do is select from
that events table as an example,
timestamp as of and you provide that
particular timestamp. Not only that, you
can provide other things, right? For
example, what you can do is there's
something called snapshot. So, every
commit you do is a snapshot and it goes
with an ID and you will say, "Select
star from that again the events table."
And you'll say, "I need this particular
version." Right? And you will say,
"Version as of." And you provide that
version. Okay, so it lets you go in the
past to get that particular state. And
this really is very powerful when you
want to inspect data. Let's say you have
GDPR compliance, right? And it really
lets you see how your data changed. And
sometime miss- takenly mess up the data,
right? You can go back and recover it
from the past. You don't have to do
rollbacks. It automatically is a feature
of Iceberg.
>> The idea of GDPR compliance as an
example from this, it sounds very
interesting. I didn't quite get how that
example illustrates GDPR. Could you
explain that a bit more detail?
>> Sure. In GDPR essentially, there's a
concept of right to be forgotten. You
want your records to be deleted. You
don't want to be remembered, right? And
what you can do is if you can go back
and show that this particular time the
particular query was deleted. It may not
be the right example here, but another
thing you could do is you need to also
remove the metadata related to that. If
you can remove that, it deletes all the
link between that parquet file that you
have stored and the metadata and you can
show what you have done in the past.
>> That is an interesting example. What I
think you meant is somebody's auditing
you or customer says, can you prove that
I've been forgotten? You could show that
5 days ago the record was there or as of
5 days ago the record was there and as
of today it's not. But, the data might
still be somewhere on disk. It's simply
inaccessible because nothing links to
it.
>> That's why I was saying like it may not
be the right example here because you
really have to delete the data, the
parquet files and the metadata link. So,
there shouldn't be any memory there.
But, the good idea will here is like if
you do timestamp as of, it gets into the
weeds of it, right? If you do timestamp
as of, it should not be able to show you
anything because you want all of the
data to be deleted for the compliance
reasons.
>> That's an interesting example, maybe not
a correct example. Do you have any other
examples of a use case for the time
travel queries?
>> Sure. Think of an example, team ran a
delete job that was too broad, right? It
was supposed to run delete 500 records,
but it deleted 2 million records, right?
So, with Iceberg you can run a command
like rollback as we do in the old
worlds, right? And you can rollback the
previous snapshot. You tell it, okay,
this is the previous snapshot I want to
go to and your data is back in seconds.
>> That is a very timely example, Zahir,
because we now have stories reaching the
tech news about people enabling AI
agents to talk to their database and the
AI agent has inadvertently deleted too
broadly, that would be a very useful
feature.
>> Yes, it is very, very much beneficial
and I have seen a lot of AI workloads
really value it. No one wants to be in a
situation where wherein you have you
delete and make that mess and then have
to explain, I executed it without even
reading it like it was too broad, but
it's tool in your toolbox that really
helps you feel secure.
>> You mentioned that it supports inserts
and updates. Clearly, your database
product is of no use if there's no way
of getting data into it, but is the
overall architecture highly read
optimized at the expense of rights
performance being sacrificed?
>> It's a essential Iceberg. I would put it
at for analytical workloads. First of
all, so and secondly, I would assume
most of the workloads would be for the
read purposes, but it doesn't mean you
can't do rights. So the rights I would
imagine in my world would be more of a
bulk rights instead of transactional
rights. Say it won't be a teller like
rights, but it'll be oh, you're doing
bulk million rows rights. Now, those
rights can be happen in two with it two
things that happen. There's a concept of
copy on right and merge on read. So if
you want I can go deep into it and
basically it defines how the re reads
what should be done or how the rights
should be done. And just a little bit of
primer, copy on rights essentially means
let's say if you're doing any some DML
operation, right? It will rewrite the
new file. So assume you have thousands
of parquet files in one parquet file
which is 100 MB or 100 GB, you have 1
million records, but you only want to
change one record. What it will do is
it'll rewrite the whole new file, right?
It's great in terms of read because
it'll be faster and referencing to the
new file. And there's another concept of
merge on read in which what it does is
it maintains the same files, but adds a
kind of a sticky note to that file or
this particular record was deleted. But
when you're reading, your computing is
computing that oh, I need to do this 10
records minus one and present you the
nine records. And that's how you define
optimize for your workloads.
>> I would like now to get more of a deep
dive into the read and write paths
including the structure of the catalog
and the metadata. I think this would be
a good time to ask you to define parquet
because you've mentioned that a few
times and I think it will be important.
So, let's do parquet first and then do
the architecture and metadata.
>> I would think of parquet as a file
format. So, just like you have dot xlsx
for Excel, you'll have dot parquet. The
advantage or before going to advantage,
I'll describe it. It's a columnar
storage meaning say you have a table or
Excel sheet that we are aware of and it
has one column with names. It's stored
by the names. It doesn't store by the
row. So, it's columnar but it's also not
only that it can be compressed. So, it's
at least three to four times smaller in
size than your Excel file per se, right?
So, it's you can store a lot more data
in a lot smaller of a file, right? And
each column is stored contiguously on
disk. So, when it is being read, it's
faster because it's stored together,
right? The column. And then another
thing that it has advantage of is that
it is self-describing meaning the schema
is in there in the file footer of the
parquet. And the compression is highly
effective. Another thing, I don't want
to go super technical but something
called predicate pushdown when you're
telling like what filter inside the file
you want to do without doing the full
scan which lets you be more performant
when you're reading it, right? And then
another thing that I really like about
the parquet is or other engineers do as
well, you can have complex types like
structs, arrays, and maps if you want to
do that, right? So, when you're doing
any reads, it read only the age column
as an example but also note that be
performant when reading it.
>> I could guess that columnar formats are
highly compressible because
particularly domain-specific
data tends to have a very few values or
a small range. Now, the predicate push
down, is that something where the file
may be organized in such a way that if
you're looking for, give one example,
values greater than 10, it can figure
out it doesn't need to read the entire
file to get values in that range, so it
reduces the amount of IO.
>> Exactly. That's precisely right. You're
reducing the IO, and uh with that
predicate push down, it all is only to
that block where the data is. And within
Parquet called row groups and those kind
of things in the whole architecture, it
goes there and find that information.
>> What I'd like to do, I'll give you some
discretion in how you want to organize
this, but walk through either read or
write paths or both, and to incorporate
the Parquet files, the catalog, the
metadata, how they are all working
together to give the user the query. How
did you want to approach that?
>> I can give an example of a read, but
before that, I think it's it'll be great
service for the audience that we explain
what the Iceberg architecture looks
like, so that when I talk about it, they
will follow, right?
>> Okay, let's do architecture and then
read.
>> Sure. So, I'll think of it in three
layers, right? And it's a tree structure
I would think of. On the very top would
sit your catalogs, right? And it can be
any catalog that you can plug in. A lot
of Iceberg compatible rest catalogs, to
put it simply again, you can use any
catalog to talk to Iceberg tables,
right? And in simple words, as I
explained before, catalog answers the
question, where is your table X, right?
It points to the current metadata file.
And the catalog will have the
information about the metadata JSON
file. It has the latest version of that
table JSON file. So, say if the table
has changed, it would know which the
latest metadata file is. And then,
that metadata JSON file, in fact, in
turn, has information about the manifest
list. And manifest list is a Avro file.
It has information about your, let's
say, partitions in a table, right? And
what it does is, it helps you prune the
partitions or help you prune the files
you don't need. And it has first level
of pruning here. And then, that manifest
list, in turn, has information about the
manifest files. It's again a Avro file.
And that manifest file, what it does is,
it maintains the statistics about the
data files, the Parquet files we were
talking about. And those manifest files
have per file stats. So, so, let's say a
Parquet I have 100 Parquet files. For
each Parquet file, it will have details
about what the min and the max values by
column, how many rows were there in in
particular
Parquet file, right? What kind of
operation was it? So, it maintains all
of that rich metadata. So, that's the
kind of a whole architecture. And it's
very rich in that. So, now, let's talk
about the read pattern as an example,
right? So, now, I want to read where my
table events is. I'm going to go and I'm
going to write a command, select star
from events. As soon as I do that, the
catalog will answer the question, where
is the latest file for events? It finds
that the latest version is V5
metadata.json. That's the latest file.
And in that JSON file, it will have
bunch of information. But, within that
bunch of information will be one key
thing, which is called snapshot. And it
will tell you what latest snapshot did.
We were talking about it as as part of
the time travel a minute ago. And that
snapshot will have a pointer to the
manifest list. And that manifest list
will have all the information about the
partitions and anything you need. And
then it will take me, "Okay, this is the
AAA.avro file. Now, let's go to that
file." And it will have the manifest
files there. When it goes to the
manifest file, it will have all the
details about the files it needs to
read.
So, say I've did select star from
events, but now I want to do select star
from events where date is July of 2025,
right? So, it knows which file has the
min and the max value of July. And it
will only go and read that file. So, it
don't have to pass through the
directories or anything. It just so rich
in metadata that it can't pass through
and only read those data files at the
bottom.
>> The example you gave there covers a
column in which the column is a time
value. So, to avoid having time appear
twice, say we were measuring some value
that's not time like the state in the
United States,
the time dimension that's expressed
through the time travel, if I understand
that, is in this tree at the snapshot
layer. So, if you have a time travel,
you would go down to that point in the
tree where the snapshot corresponds to
your time travel cutoff. That's a guess.
Is that correct?
>> Yeah, so the metadata.json will have
that snapshot log. And in that snapshot
log, it's essentially a log, but also
the timeline, right? So, when we do as
of that particular timeline, that's what
it uses as its a cutoff time.
>> Okay. So, you took us through read and
are talking a little bit about time
travel read. The other major operation
would be write. So, can you walk us
through the write going through all
those layers of the tree?
>> Absolutely. So, say you are an engine,
you are trying to do an DML operation or
trying to do an insert, right? You
generally you can define what size of a
file you would like to populate in the
storage. Let's say you want to maintain
256 GB of files, right? And you want to
write 2560. So, it will create 10 files
for you. And the way it does it, it
starts from bottom up. So, first it will
write the files in your storage, object
storage. But other engines querying
wouldn't know because it hasn't written
that snapshot or that metadata yet. As
soon as it writes it, it will write the
manifest file. In manifest file, then it
will populate, okay, these are the files
I populated. These are the min and the
max values per column, right? And other
commit time and those kind of things.
And then once it creates that manifest
file, it will create a manifest list.
And that manifest list will be like,
okay, this is the manifest file I need
to refer. And this is part of X
snapshot. And then it will populate the
partition information, say, right? If
you have any partition information.
It'll populate that there. Once it's
done with all of this, it will try to
write a very final thing, the metadata
JSON. And that's where it does compare
and swap. It starts with the latest
version and then compares and So, what
it does is it tries to figure out, okay,
I started writing those 10 files, but in
the meantime, did the metadata JSON
change? If it changed, it has to redo
the newer version of the JSON, which
otherwise would conflict, or otherwise
it will just do version plus one .json
and write that metadata JSON file. And
that will become the current file. Going
on forward, there will be read
isolation. Anything that is coming into
read it will start reading from that
particular commit.
>> We want our rights to be atomic. Now,
this process you described there are
multiple files that need to be changed.
Something could fail before it's
completed the process.
Does it depend on the final step being
created and that the system can
tolerate, let's say, dangling references
or files with nothing pointing to them
from prior failures?
>> It solves all the problems that you
talked about. They They are seeing the
problem with the hive as well, right?
So, there are two kind of thing. One is
read isolation, one is write. In terms
of reads, what it does is like for the
audience, if you start at 2:00 p.m.
reading something and at 2:01 p.m.
something changed, but they give you
results at 2:05, you still see the
result at 2:00 p.m. It locked you there
at the very first time you started
reading. But for the rights, the way it
does it, it's optimistic write
isolation. To put it simply, say Robert
is trying to write and Sahil is trying
to write. Whoever first writes get the
JSON, the other person will get the
rejection. And it will go to that
engine, okay, Sahil, Robert committed,
go back and start writing the engines.
But what it doesn't have to do is to
rewrite the file. It only has to write
the metadata. The files stay the same.
But assume something happens, the world
crashes and everything and say it's all
of the operations leave in between. You
have those orphan files, but they are
not rendered anywhere because there's no
reference in the metadata. So, they
won't give you corrupt reads. The only
thing you will have to do is clean up
your storage. And that operation has to
be done to remove the orphan files if
you identify. But those are very rare
scenarios.
>> Does Iceberg support anything for
managing the size of data either I no
longer need historical time travel
beyond a certain date in the past or I
can de-res the data by going from every
single change to once a week or
something like Postgres vacuum that is
just cleaning up spaces created by write
operations.
>> Yeah, there's something called snapshot
expiry.
So, let's say you're doing a lot of DML
operation every 15 minutes and you don't
necessarily need snapshot from a week
ago or week ago later, right? What you
do is you can configure through engines
that I want to expire or remove the
snapshots after a certain date. And
that's where you will see, okay, you
can't go back beyond a certain date. And
that's a decisions team make depending
on their workloads, what they want to
do, those kind of things, right? And
similarly for the I think you talked
about the vacuum, there's something
called vacuum full in Postgres, if I'm
not wrong. So, essentially what it means
is say you have committed small files
over a period of time. And over the
weekend, you get smaller chunk of files,
for example. But over the weekend, you
get a proper trend. But what you want to
do is you want to make sure your whole
bucket is clean and you don't want to
maintain small files because it still
has to read it, still has to do
everything. What you can do is you can
merge all small files into a standard
large files, which is best for your read
patterns and it's called data
compaction. And a lot of engines provide
that kind of service when you do manage
service with them, but you can manage by
yourself as well.
>> Most databases have something like the
query planner that decides what order to
access different tables in what in a
join.
We haven't talked about joins, but does
Iceberg support joins and does it have a
query planner or is that process you
described where it's walking through the
metadata to find what it needs, is that
the query planner?
>> Yeah, so Iceberg handles all of those
things to an engine. What it does is it
tells you, "Okay, this is the metadata I
have
and this is the metadata you should pass
through to do the query fetch." But, it
doesn't tell you, "This is how you
should do it." It tells you the spec. It
tells you that this is what I have. This
is how you can traverse through the tree
of the metadata, but it doesn't tell
you, "Okay, this is up to the engines to
implement."
>> So far, we've been talking about a
single table or we haven't been
specific. Does Iceberg support joins?
>> Yes, Iceberg does support joins. You can
connect multiple tables together to have
a rendered results as you need. You can
join Iceberg to Iceberg or in case of
several engines, let's say have their
custom table format, you can connect
Iceberg to a custom table format, but
that's something engine does. But, to
answer your question, yes.
>> So, my next question is going to be is
there a query planner?
But, since Iceberg is not an engine,
it's just a format,
what's the right question I should be
asking?
>> So, to first we answer the question that
it does support join, yes. And to a
follow-up question, it's very much
engine dependent. Iceberg does provide
the stats for better join planning,
right? But, it doesn't execute the
joins.
Your engine has to plan those joins
architecturally the query plan per se
based on that, but Iceberg doesn't
prescribe that.
>> Are there multiple engines in the
marketplace from different vendors? Are
they commercial? Are they open source?
>> Yeah, there are multiple engine options
you have. You have proprietary ones, the
commercial ones, and you have the open
ones. You can use Spark, the Flink, the
Trino, which is open source. But, you
can use Snowflake, you can use
Databricks, you can use BigQuery,
anything which is compatible to the
Iceberg spec can use it.
>> You also mentioned there are multiple
options for catalog. As I was reading
about this, I found this list consisting
of Hadoop, Hive, AWS Glue, and some
others. What are some of the more
popular catalogs?
>> Sure. AWS Glue is one of them, and AWS
Glue recently became compatible with
IRC, which is Iceberg rest compatible,
right? And then you have Snowflake's
Horizon, Databricks Unity Catalog, and
Hive Metastore. But Hive Metastore is
usually I haven't seen being used a lot,
just because with cloud at a Hive
Metastore was built better for the HDFS
file and everything, but it's it's one
of the options as well.
>> What are some differentiators between
different catalogs?
>> Very good question. So, it really varies
what you are trying to do. So, let me
put it this way. As we talked about
Iceberg spec, there's several versions
of it. Version one, version two, version
three. So, as an example, the current
version that is GA is version three,
which supports nanoseconds time support.
So, not all
catalogs would support it. So, you have
to think through how the implementations
are, what you're looking into, say
Spark is writing it, Snowflake is
reading it.
Can that catalog support it, right? And
then another thing you want to see is
how the RBAX are handled. So, say since
this is interoperable, you want to make
sure that your governance gets applied
from one side to another, right? So, say
you have access via Spark, but you don't
have access via Snowflake to a certain
area. You want to make sure you have the
right roles, and the governance is
handled via the catalog. How strong are
they with the governance, how they vent
the credentials to the storage, those
aspects. So, it's a variety, and I would
evaluate in a way wherein what's my use
case.
>> I I to move now for the last part of the
interview talking about the bigger
picture of Iceberg in the application
architecture for an entire application.
The idea of a CRUD application is
extremely widespread. Almost everything
we use on the internet for business is
some kind of CRUD application that
writes into OLTP. By application, I mean
something has a database, a middle tier,
and a user interface. What would be uh
some examples of a database application
where Iceberg is the data layer? What is
that application doing? What is its
architecture?
>> I can give one of my examples that I
recently implemented. We had clickstream
data coming in, and the clickstream data
landed in Postgres. Postgres is OLTP.
And then, from there, it landed via the
Pulsar. Pulsar Apache Pulsar is again
for streaming as well as uh managing the
queues. What it did is it holds data for
about 15 minutes, and then pushes to
Snowflake. And then, when it lands to
Snowflake, that's where you will do a
lot of your cleaning up, transformations
you want to do, and you prepare it or
curate it for other teams. And then,
ultimately,
the teams wanted to implement the ML
work or the model on the Spark side. And
that's where the interoperability come
in. They were able to use the Snowflake
engine to do a lot of my transformations
and loading for the right tables. And
but the ML teams could leverage the
Spark engine for the ML workloads to buy
just accessing the table that were
written by Snowflake on S3. And to
summarize this, I would put it in a way
wherein your multiple teams need access
to the same data,
but you don't want to don't want to have
a redundant storage in terms of just
okay for the same use case. You don't
want to have that. It's better you don't
do it. Secondly, I have seen a lot of
teams do doing the similar
transformation or almost similar
transformation just to give different
kind of data to different teams, right?
It reduces that. Another thing is, if
you have use cases wherein you want to
do anything analytical, that's where I
will use it. Again, AI is one of the use
cases that's uh
getting very much popular in which what
happens is you can have Git-like
branching and you can do AB testing on
the data with Nessie catalog and you do
branch the data into two layers and do
analysis on both layers.
>> By AI being an application, are we
talking more about training or
fine-tuning or about using the data to
drive inference of models you already
have in order to evaluate the models or
what do we mean by AI?
>> Okay, I just the training the data. If
you're training the data with data set A
versus B and you have a branch-like
structure, data branch, not a Git
branch, data branch-like structure, you
can have A and B comparison while
training and do analysis.
>> Well, see here we've covered Iceberg
from beginning to end. Before we wrap
up, is anything else about Iceberg that
you'd like listeners to take away?
>> What I would say is a very exciting
field and it's a very exciting world of
the Iceberg. Now, Iceberg team is
working and collaborating on the version
V4. It's not final yet, but it's going
towards even better product. And another
thing that I've been noticing in
industry is that vendors are converging
to Iceberg as a standard. They are now
not limiting themselves to their own
proprietary one. So, I think it's a good
time to adopt. Another thing that I
would recommend teams to take away is be
more involved in Apache's dev list uh
for the Iceberg. You'll get to know how
it's developing, what the discussion
themes are, what the common themes are,
and you'll get to know how things are
developing in the world of iceberg. It's
a truly, truly exciting time to be a
learning iceberg.
>> Before we sign off, would you like to
direct listeners anywhere they can find
you,
your publications, or any projects
you're involved with?
>> Absolutely. You can reach out to me on
my LinkedIn. My LinkedIn is Sahil Walia,
as you see my name, and then Syracuse,
Syracuse, New York. And I can be reached
on I have a medium page where I publish
articles, and you can look at my Google
Scholar, as well.
>> Sahil, thank you very much, and thank
you for speaking to Software Engineering
Radio.
>> Thank you, Robert. It was great chatting
with you. I appreciate it.
>> For Software Engineering Radio, this has
been Robert Blumen. Thank you for
listening.
>> [music]
>> Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website, or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
se-radio.slack.com.
[music]
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5. [music]
Thanks for listening.